Finding Aid for Clarence T. Johnston Papers, 1888-1941
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Clarence T. Johnston papers 1888-1941
Johnston, Clarence Thomas, 1872-1970.
Professor of engineering at the University of Michigan. Photos of Johnston's personal and family life in Wyoming and Michigan, including student activities at the University of Michigan; photos of his work on water projects in the West and in Egypt; and photos of Camp Davis, the summer engineering camp of the University of Michigan in Cheboygan Co., Michigan.
88344 Aa2 UAm
10 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection has been brought together from a number of sources, including Robert Harris (University of Michigan Chief Marshall (donor 5375 ), Kenneth Soderbeck (donor 5126 ) and Don Bryant (donor 5127 ). All these accessions came to the library between 1971 and 1981. An earlier accession came from an unknown source.
The collection is open for research. However boxes 1-7 (glass negatives) are for staff use only.
Clarence Thomas Johnston was born on a farm in Littleton, Colorado on October 23, 1872. His mother, Melissa Drummond Johnston, was of Scotch and Welsh ancestry. His father, James Albert Johnston, was of Scotch-Irish and Dutch ancestry. James Johnston pursued a variety of careers: he was a farmer, miner, railway and canal builder, superintendent of irrigation systems, administrative officer in Wyoming, and finally, a banker.
C.T. Johnston married Bessie Vreeland of Cheyenne, Wyoming on October 20, 1897. It is perhaps telling of his dedication to his career that Johnston named his two sons, Clarence Nettleton and Franklin Davis, after engineers. Clarence bore as middle name the surname of E.S. Nettleton, James Johnston's partner in irrigation work, and Franklin was given the name of Professor Davis from the University of Michigan.
C.T. Johnston was educated in country schools and attended high school in Cheyenne, Wyoming, 1885-1890. He received a B.S. in civil engineering from the University of Michigan in 1895, and did graduate work in absentia from the University of Michigan, 1897-1899, to receive a C.E. degree. Johnston spent the summers of 1892-1894 in field work under the State Engineer of Wyoming. His later specialty in irrigation, drainage, and riparian rights shows roots in the work from this time. In July 1893, he completed the surveys and plans for a reservoir for the Wyoming Development Company. The reservoir had a water line of 35 miles, and a 1 1/4 mile-long dam that was 35 feet high. Later in the summer of 1893, he surveyed a line over 100 miles long for a large canal from the North Platte River in eastern Wyoming. From fall 1894 to spring 1895, Johnston laid out placer ground over 9,000 acres for the West Side Mining Company in Routte County, Colorado. This project included maintenance of 30 miles of canal, installing a placer mining plant, and submitting a report for treating amalgam.
Between 1896 and 1898, Johnston measured streams for the U.S. Geological Survey and worked in the office of the State Engineer. Early in the spring of 1897, he was involved in the construction of a large reservoir near Wheatland, Wyoming. The project involved tunnels, reinforced concrete design, and special hydraulic structures. In the fall of 1897, Johnston helped Capt. H.M. Chittenden in a study of reservoir sites in Colorado and Wyoming.
Johnston was appointed Assistant State Engineer of Wyoming in November, 1897. He held that position until the spring of 1899, at which time he was appointed Assistant Chief of Irrigation Investigation for the U.S. Department of Agriculture. This work included the study of drainage as well. Regionally, the work encompassed all western states and the South (in connection with rice cultivation). For a year in 1901 and 1902, Johnston pursued further study of irrigation and drainage in foreign countries. He studied Spain, Southern France, Northern Italy, Algiers, and particularly Egypt. In 1903, Johnston resigned from government service to accept the position of State Engineer of Wyoming. In that office, he had administrative charge of all water use within the borders of Wyoming. During the period of Johnston's tenure from 1903 to 1911, over 10,000 rights to use water were determined and plans were approved for many million dollars worth of construction. During this same period, Johnston had charge of municipal work and water power development in Wyoming and other states. The water system of Cheyenne was one of the large undertakings of this character where a series of reservoirs was built, two of the dams being approximately 100 feet high.
On February 1, 1911, C.T. Johnston was appointed to a newly created professorship of Surveying and Geodesy in the School of Engineering at the University of Michigan. Until this time, surveying and geodesy was a part of the regular civil engineering curriculum. Under Johnston's direction, additional elective courses for the specialty in surveying were organized. A separate Department of Geodesy and Surveying was established and chaired by Johnston in 1921. Degrees were first granted from the department in 1922-1923, but the department was discontinued in 1941.
Upon Johnston's arrival at Michigan in 1911, he assumed direction of the School of Engineering's summer surveying camp. The camp was located near Cheboygan in northern Michigan at Douglas Lake. It was known as Camp Davis after Professor Joseph B. Davis from the school. Other faculty with whom Johnston worked closely at the camp were Professor Howard B. Merrick (who had run the camp until Johnston's arrival) and Assoc. Professor Hugh Brodie.
Johnston did much to rebuild Camp Davis over the years 1914-1920. However, a standing rivalry with the Biological Station at Douglas Lake prompted interest in relocating the surveying camp. Johnston led explorations of sites in Wyoming, and in 1929 the Regents of the University purchased 120 acres near Jackson Hole, 75 miles south of Yellowstone National Park. The Jackson site became the new Camp Davis. In 1941, C.T. Johnston retired from the School of Engineering.
The photographs and glass negatives in the C.T. Johnston collection span the dates 1888-1928. They document personal and professional experiences of Clarence T. Johnston, a successful engineer who left Wyoming to teach in the College of Engineering at the University of Michigan.
The personal photographs are from a time when people were already beginning to feel at ease before a camera, but the Johnston pictures are still notable for their warmth and informality. Relatives and friends have purposefully gathered for picture-taking sessions, but most of the images captured do not have the feeling of being strictly posed. Johnston's wife, Bessie, is chewing on a blade of grass in one picnic scene; his son Franklin has his face screwed up in mischief for several photographs.
The beginning of Johnston's relationship with Bessie Vreeland is documented with a group of photographs of her home and relatives. Although there are no wedding pictures in this collection, the Johnston children were photographed as the family grew.
The photographs also reflect the comfort and quality of life in Wyoming at the turn of the century--not all of the state was relegated to cowboys and the range. The Wild West stereotype is undermined by images of a very civilly planned Cheyenne Park and of pleasantries such as a colonial costume party celebrating George Washington's birthday. On the other hand, a young woman in fashionable mutton sleeves aiming her rifle at some object beyond the camera's range reminds one that the picnic she is attending could only be taking place in a spirited western state.
The photographs of family and friends on camping and picnic outings reflect the early 20th-century interest in the "great outdoors" as a national pastime. Johnston's family was doubly inclined to recreation in the open environment by the nature of his engineering work and by their convenient location in Wyoming. Throughout the collection are images of great natural beauty. Johnston traveled extensively through Yellowstone National Park, the Grand Tetons, and the Jackson Lake area. The series therefore yields photographs of some of the most beautiful scenery in North America. It is likely that Johnston would have pursued photography as an amateur even if he were not professionally using it. There are photographs that show Johnston's engineering cameras and tripods, but there are also photographs that capture his two sons playing with smaller family cameras on the picnic blanket. Also, there seems to be an even mix of engineer's eye and tourist's appetite on the travel pictures from Egypt and Tacoma, Washington.
The Johnston photograph collection is notable as a sampling of early engineering photography. Photography was first added to the civil engineering curriculum at Michigan in 1890. As a surveyor, Johnston seems to have enthusiastically embraced the practice.
The notes on his photographs are full of directional descriptions and identification of vantage points such as "Dome Lake looking southwest from north side." There are several panoramic sequences as Johnston sought to comprehensively document the views for his surveys. In addition to affecting the composition of his photographs, engineering was the subject of many of his work-related photographs. The period up to 1911 includes a building demolition, several canal and dam projects, and surveying trips. Most of the Camp Davis series documents engineering projects undertaken by students to rebuild the camp. The photographs from 1928 in the Camp Davis series are from the search for a new camp site in Wyoming.
While the bulk of the collection is comprised of photographic prints and negatives, scattered papers are also present and include biographical material and topical files relating to Johnston's personal, religious, and professional activities.
The C.T. Johnston collection of glass negatives includes three series that roughly parallel the chronology of Johnston's personal life and work. These series are "Personal and family life," "Work (engineering and surveying projects)," and "Camp Davis." Within each series are several groups of photographs arranged by existing negative numbering systems, or in the absence of a system, by date or topical groups. Most of the original negative sleeves were annotated with dates and notes explaining the photographs. When the numbers on the negative sleeves were sequential, these numbers were retained in the notes, supplemented with a date, and enclosed in brackets, i.e. 1916 [22]. When no negative numbers existed, a numbering system was supplied. The system was based on a four-digit sequence with the thousand number corresponding to the box in which the glass plate is stored. Descriptive captions were also supplied for most of the unidentified negatives. All supplied negative numbers, dates, and captions are closed in parentheses.
Unless noted otherwise, the glass negatives in this collection are all 6" x 8". Two groups of plates measuring 5" x 7", "School days" and "Family and friends, Wyoming," are located at the beginning of the "Personal and family life" series. Another group of plates measuring 5" x 7", "Early reservoirs and surveying," are located within the chronological arrangement of the "Work (engineering and surveying)" series.
The glass plate negatives comprise the first seven boxes of this collection. Boxes 8 and 9 contain prints, most of which are cyanotypes. As the organization of the prints parallels the negatives, a separate list of the prints is not necessary. The description list includes box numbers that reflect the parallel arrangement of negatives to prints, i.e. 8:2 means that the print for a negative in Box 2 will be found in Box 8.
Subjects
Engineers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; First Congregational Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Johnston, Clarence Thomas, 1872-1970.; Michigan. Relicted Lands Commission.; State Drain Commissioners Association (Mich.); University of Michigan. Student Religious Association.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Senate Council.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Boats.; Burt Lake (Mich.); Camp Davis (University of Michigan); Camping.; Canals.; Dams.; Douglas Lake (Mich.); Egypt.; Grand Teton National Park (Wyo.); Idaho.; Indians of North America.; Irrigation.; Johnston, Clarence Thomas, 1872-1970.; Johnston family.; Photographers.; Surveying--Wyoming.; Surveying--Michigan.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.; Wyoming.; Yellowstone National Park.
Genre/Form:
Cyanotypes.; Glass photonegatives.; Photographs.
- Personal and Family Life Photos
  The first series of photographs is "Personal and family life." Predominant in this series are pictures of Johnston's wife, Bessie Vreeland "of 1822 Pebrican St.," and her relatives and children. A group of houses and buildings in Cheyenne from 1904-1905, two camping trips, and undated pictures from a trip to Tacoma, Washington follow.
  - School Days, University of Michigan (5"x7")
    - 1894
      - Theresa? and Retta Jo Christmas (Box 8:1)
        [54]
      - Indian Ghost Dance (Box 8:1)
        [266]
    - 1895
      - View on the Huron from peach orchard, Ann Arbor circa 1895 (Box 8:1)
        [75]
      - Northwest corner, Campus, Ann Arbor (Box 8:1)
        [77]
      - Camp at Fountain Point, Sunday afternoon 1895 (Box 8:1)
        (Lefavour? missing)
        [127]
      - Roll call 7 am, Fountain Point, MI (Box 8:1)
        [129]
      - Lefavour, King, Johnston on boat dock, Carp Lake, MI (Box 8:1)
        [130]
      - Group in dock, Carp Lake, MI (Box 8:1)
        [131]
      - Group Sunday afternoon, Fountain Point, MI (Box 8:1)
        [132]
      - King, Lefavour, Johnston, Fountain Point, MI (Box 8:1)
        [133]
      - Prof. Davis and tent, Fountain Point, MI (Box 8:1)
        [135]
  - Family and Friends, Wyoming (5"x7")
    - 1895
      - Group at Mrs. Woods, 19th & Copan?, Cheyenne, WY October 10, 1895 (Box 8:1)
        [243]
      - Indians Prior Agency (Box 8:1)
        [374]
      - Indians Prior Agency (Box 8:1)
        [375]
    - 1896
      - Four horse stage coach, Baggs, WY May 1, 1896 (Box 8:1)
        [196]
      - Six girls and wheels, 408 W. 23 September 28, 1896 (Box 8:1)
        [21]
    - 1897
      - Effie, Louie by Bessie (Box 8:1)
        [269]
      - Miss Shane, Emma O'B., Bessie, Effie, Gussie July 1897 (Box 8:1)
        [298]
      - Group 408 W. 23, 20 girls August 2, 1897 (Box 8:1)
        [300]
      - (Group below falls, picnic outing) July 5, 1897 (Box 8:1)
      - Large group below falls, picnic July 5, 1897 (Box 8:1)
        [445]
      - Group on Middle Crow Creek Picnic July 5, 1897 (Box 8:1)
        [446]
      - Group at Stephenson's Picnic July 5, 1897 (Box 8:1)
        [447]
    - 1898
      - 1822 Pebrican? April 1898 (Box 8:1)
        [341]
      - Louie, Frank, and William, 1822 Pebrioau? July 10, 1898 (Box 8:1)
        [361]
      - William Booker Sr. & Jr., Bessie of 1822 (Box 8:1)
      - Pebrican? July 10, 1898 (Box 8:1)
        [362]
      - Dr. Carey's house August 1898 (Box 8:1)
        [370]
      - McGraw's house 20 miles up Bear River from Evanston September 12, 1898 (Box 8:1)
        [376]
      - Hay stacks in Christensen's and Whitney's field, 20 miles below Evanston September 14, 1898 (Box 8:1)
        [379]
    - 1899
      - Clarence N. Johnston May 8, 1899 (Box 8:1)
        [471]
      - Clarence N. Johnston (7 months) May 31, 1899 (Box 8:1)
        [477]
      - Clarence N. Johnston (7 months) May 31, 1899 (Box 8:1)
        [478]
      - Clarence N. Johnston, 10 months, Gussie Johnston (Box 8:1)
        [482]
    - 1900
      - C.N. Johnston January 20, 1900 (Box 8:1)
        [487]
      - C.N. Johnston March 30, 1900 (Box 8:1)
        [490]
      - C.N. Johnston March 30, 1900 (Box 8:1)
        [491]
      - Overalls group of babies, 1822 Pebrican? St. May 13, 1900 (Box 8:1)
        [502]
      - Group of babies, 1822 Pebrican? St. April 29, 1900 (Box 8:1)
        [504]
      - Group of babies, 1822 Pebrican? St. April 29, 1900 (Box 8:1)
        [506]
      - William Booker, Jr. May 6, 1900 (Box 8:1)
        [507]
      - House, 1822 Pebrican? St. June 3, 1900 (Box 8:1)
        [509]
      - Shingles House June 3, 1900 (Box 8:1)
        [510]
      - House, 1822 Pebrican? June 3, 1900 (Box 8:1)
        [511]
      - CNJ July 7, 1900 (Box 8:1)
        [1001]
      - CNJ July 7, 1900 (Box 8:1)
        [1002]
      - CNJ July 22,1900 (Box 8:1)
        [1003]
      - CNJ December 1900 (Box 8:1)
        [1004]
    - circa 1900
      - (Group on porch with CTJ, Bessie and CNJ, and Gussie, 1822 Pebrican?) (Box 8:1)
        [1005]
      - (Group in parlor, Bessie on right) (Box 8:1)
        [1006]
    - 1901
      - Group, Mrs. Nettleton's February 22, 1901 (Box 8:1)
        [1007]
      - Franklin just-out-of the bath March 1901 (Box 8:1)
        [1008]
      - (Franklin in high chair) (Box 8:1)
        [1009]
      - Clarence with his cart April 1901 (Box 8:1)
        [1010]
      - Clarence and Franklin, June 8,1901, 2 plates (Box 8:1)
        [1011-1012]
      - Franklin June 23, 1901 (Box 8:1)
        [1013]
      - Franklin June 23, 1901 (Box 8:1)
        [1014]
      - Bessie and Franklin August 18, 1901 (Box 8:1)
        [1015]
      - Clarence August 18, 1901 (Box 8:1)
        [1016]
    - 1902
      - Franklin June 1902 (Box 8:1)
        [1017]
      - Clarence June 1902 (Box 8:1)
        [1018]
    - circa 1903
      - (Clarence and Franklin) (Box 8:1)
        [1019]
      - 190? (Clarence and Franklin) (Box 8:1)
        [1020]
    - 1888
      - Bessie's class (Box 8:1)
        [1021]
    - 1903
      - Gleason, Johnston, and Williams children July, 1903 (Box 8:1)
        [1022]
    - 1904
      - Consistory Class of January 1904 (Box 8:1)
        [1023]
      - Louise, Franklin, Clarence, Anna June 19, 1904 (Box 8:1)
        [1024]
      - (portrait of CTJ), 2 plates (Box 8:1)
        [1025-1026]
      - (Clarence N., Franklin, and cousin), 2 plates (Box 8:1)
        [1027-1028]
      - (Bessie and Gussie, Clarence N. and Franklin, and cousin) (Box 8:1)
        [1029]
      - C.T. Johnston, far right (when State Engineer of Wy?) 1903-1911 (Box 8:1)
        [1030]
      - C.T. Johnston, far right (when State Engineer of Wy?) 1903-1911 (Box 8:1)
        [1031]
  - Cheyenne, WY
    - 1904
      - Cheyenne Park June 26, 1904 (Box 8:1)
        [1032]
      - (Cheyenne Park) (Box 8:1)
        [1033]
      - (Cheyenne, Carnegie Public Library), 3 plates (Box 8:1)
        [1034-1036]
      - (Cheyenne State Capitol?) (Box 8:1)
        [1037]
      - (park in Cheyenne), 2 plates (Box 8:1)
        [1038-1039]
      - (Cheyenne, Masonic Lodge), 2 plates (Box 8:1)
        [1040-1041]
      - (House, front view) (Box 8:1)
        [1042]
      - (House, left angle, front view) (Box 8:1)
        [1043]
      - (House, right angle, front view) (Box 8:1)
        [1044]
    - 1905
      - (Snow scene) April 1905 (Box 8:1)
        [1045]
      - (Snow on tree-lined street) April 1905 (Box 8:1)
        [1046]
      - (Tree-lined street with horse and buggy) (Box 8:1)
        [1047]
      - (Horse and buggy) (Box 8:1)
        [1048]
  - Camping Trips
    - circa 1906
      - (Group including Bessie, Clarence N., and Franklin at a hike in mountains) (Box 8:1)
        [1049]
      - (Group of four including C.T. and Bessie Johnston) (Box 8:1)
        [1050]
      - (Two women with fishing rods, man with gun) (Box 8:1)
        [1051]
      - (Two boys, Clarence N. and Franklin?, in tree) (Box 8:1)
        [1052]
      - (Tent) (Box 8:1)
        [1053]
      - (Bessie, C.N., and Franklin in boat) (Box 8:1)
        [1054]
      - (Camp site with tent) (Box 8:1)
        [1055]
      - (Picnic group, including Bessie, C.N., and Franklin) (Box 8:1)
        [1056]
      - (Group at camp site) (Box 8:1)
        [1057]
      - (Group including Bessie, C.N., and Franklin-boys playing with camera) (Box 8:1)
        [1058]
      - (Group including C.N., Bessie, and Franklin), 3 plates (Box 8:1)
        [1059-1061]
      - (Reclining group at camp site) (Box 8:1)
        [1062]
      - (Camp site) (Box 8:1)
        [1063]
      - (Trees near camp site) (Box 8:1)
        [1064]
      - (Tents) (Box 8:1)
        [1065]
      - (Camp site) (Box 8:1)
        [1066]
  - Granite Springs Camplight Trip 1908
    - circa 1908
      - (Camp site with tent and buggy, lake in background) (Box 8:1)
        [1067]
      - (Tent and buggy viewed from across a lake) (Box 8:1)
        [1068]
      - (Tent and buggy viewed from lake) (Box 8:1)
        [1069]
      - (Two rowers in boat) (Box 8:1)
        [1070]
      - (Double exposure of lakeside camp site and group) (Box 8:1)
        [1071]
    - 1908
      - Picnic Party, flashlight, Granite Springs (Box 8:1)
        [1072]
      - Granite Crag and Granite Springs Res. (Box 8:1)
        [1073]
      - Granite Springs and Crag (Box 8:1)
        [1074]
      - (Granite Crag) (Box 8:1)
        [1075]
      - Granite Springs Res. (Box 8:1)
        [1076]
      - Granite Springs Res., Upper End, 2 plates (Box 8:1)
        [1077-1078]
      - Upper Middle Crow Creek (Box 8:1)
        [1079]
      - Yellowstone Park Trip (Box 8:1)
        [1080]
  - Tacoma, WA Trip
    - 190?
      - Unidentified photographs, Tacoma, 16 photographs (Box 8:1)
        [1081-1096]
  - Unidentified Neighborhood
    - 190?
      - (Cheyenne? Houses on street) (Box 8:1)
        [1097]
      - (Houses on street) (Box 8:1)
        [1098]
      - (House with porch) (Box 8:1)
        [1099]
      - (Elderly couple on front porch) (Box 8:1)
        [1100]
      - (Elderly couple seated on front porch) (Box 8:1)
        [1101]
      - (Distance view of elderly couple seated on front porch) (Box 8:1)
        [1102]
      - (Elderly couple seated on front porch with cat) (Box 8:1)
        [1103]
      - (Group seated on porch) (Box 8:1)
        [1104]
      - 190? (Group on porch, CTJ front center) (Box 2.8)
        [2000]
      - (Two gentlemen, interior), 2 plates (Box 2.8)
        [2001-2002]
      - (Two gentlemen seated on porch steps), 2 plates (Box 2.8)
        [2003-2004]
      - (Two gentlemen standing) (Box 2.8)
        [2005]
  - Country House undated
    - (Ranch-style country house) (Box 8:2)
      [2006]
    - (Country house with elderly couple on front lawn) (Box 8:2)
      [2007]
    - (Country house) (Box 8:2)
      [2008]
    - (Shed with car) (Box 8:2)
      [2009]
    - (Road to country house) (Box 8:2)
      [2010]
    - (Country house), 2 plates (Box 8:2)
      [2011-2012]
- Work Photos (Engineering and Surveying Projects)
  The series simply called "Work" includes chronologically arranged groups of photographs of engineering projects or surveying trips. The first several groups are chiefly of reservoirs and dam sites located in Wyoming and Colorado. Work from 1901-1902 includes pictures taken on a study trip to Egypt. 1907 contains pictures from the Twin Falls Canal and Seminole Cañon, Wyoming. The Seminole Cañon group is interesting because it includes sketches of the canyon with numbered vantage points corresponding to the negative number sequence. 1908 concentrates on geysers and water sources in Yellowstone National Park and the Jackson Lake area. 1909 and 1910 include more water-related pictures from Wheatland Development Company's Reservoir No. 2 and the Cheyenne Water Work's Chrystal Lake Dam. The final two groups include unidentified engineering projects, and a numbered but unidentified sequence of work-related scenery.
  - Building Demolition Undated
    - (Building shell, demolition) (Box 8:2)
      [2013]
    - (Building shell, CTJ on roof surveying demolition) (Box 8:2)
      [2014]